<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Behold a cry! or, A true relation of the inhumane and violent outrages of divers souldiers, constables, and others, practised upon many of the Lord's people, commonly (though falsly) called Anabaptists, at their several meetings in and about London. : Together with the violence offered some of them in Newgate (where they are now prisoners) by the fellons in the same place.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76349</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1778A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R172696</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45504291</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45504291</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171597</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76349)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171597)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2578:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Behold a cry! or, A true relation of the inhumane and violent outrages of divers souldiers, constables, and others, practised upon many of the Lord's people, commonly (though falsly) called Anabaptists, at their several meetings in and about London. : Together with the violence offered some of them in Newgate (where they are now prisoners) by the fellons in the same place.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anabaptists --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Persecution --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171597:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Behold a Cry! Or, a TRUE RELATION OF THE Inhumane and Violent OUTRAGES of divers <hi>Souldiers, Conſtables,</hi> and others, practiſed upon many of the Lord's People, commonly (though falſly) called <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> at their ſeveral Meetings in and about <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together With the Violence offered ſome of them in <hi>Newgate,</hi> (where they are now Priſoners) by the Fellons in the ſame place.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The Earth was filled with Violence, <bibl>
                     <hi>Gen. 6.11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord loveth the Righteous, but the Wicked and him that loveth Violence his Soul hateth. <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 11.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>As a roaring Lion and a ranging Bear, ſo is a wicked Ruler over the people, <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 28.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>The Prince that wanteth underſtanding is alſo a great Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour, <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 28.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>A man that doth Violence to the Blood of any perſon, ſhall flee to the Pit, let no man ſtay him, <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 28.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1662.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171597:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171597:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171597:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171597:3"/>
            <head>Behold a Cry! OR, A true RELATION of the Inhumane and Violent Outrages of divers <hi>Souldiers, Conſtables,</hi> and others, practiſed upon many of the Lord's People, commonly (though falſly) called <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> at their ſeveral Meetings, in and about <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THe ſundry and divers Abuſes that hath been offered time after time, to the free-born People of <hi>England,</hi> contrary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> and all the known Laws of the Land, the <hi>Declaration</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation</hi> of the King that now is, we cannot ſuppoſe the Nation wholly ignorant of; but how inhumanly they have been uſed, and with what violence Souldiers and others have proceeded in ſeveral places where they have in the fear of the Lord been aſſembled, their uſual manner being to come with Souldiers, which common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were moſt of them rude Youths, or Mercinary men, of the ruder and viler ſort, and they with their Muskets, and ſome with their Swords drawn, to the affrighting of Women and Children, break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſpoyling of their Goods; doing violence to their perſons, by pulling, halling, and beating ſome of them, the which they may not underſtand: Now that all, both Magiſtrates and People may be rightly informed, the mouth of Falſhood and Scandal ſtoped, and ſuch Abuſes redreſſed, we ſhall in particular give a brief hint of ſome of them, as followeth.</p>
            <p>In <hi>June</hi> 1661. there came divers rude Souldiers, Wicked, Swearing, and Debauched perſons, to the Meeting-houſe in <hi>Brick-Lane</hi> near <hi>White-Chappel,</hi> and laid hands on ſeveral men, to the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171597:4"/>number of more than twenty, who, in a peaceable manner, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of them their Warrant for their ſo doing, but they would not ſhew them any; which, one <hi>William Caſwel</hi> ſeeing, he ſaid (or to this purpoſe) <hi>That if they had a Warrant he would obey it, but if they had none, they ſhould carry him, for he would not go:</hi> With that they beat him with their Hangers about the Head, and pulled him along by force, and ſometime taking him up between three or four of them, and then leting him fall with violence into the Dirt, pulling by great force his Stomack and Breaſt againſt the Railes, inſomuch that with blowes, and falls, he is deprived of health to this day: And when (becauſe the King in his <hi>Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> bearing date <hi>January</hi> 17. 1660. declared, <hi>That if any ſhould be ſo hardy, as to ſeize the Perſons of any without Warrant,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that then they ſhould be left open to the Law to be proceeded againſt, and receive according to their Demerit:</hi>) there was ſeveral of the Actors of this Tragedy arreſted, and Sute, being according to Law, commenced againſt them, and the perſons abuſed, intending to go on; they were ſuddenly ſurpriſed, and prevented by <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> who granted a Warrant, to ſeize the Body of <hi>Thomas Hull</hi> and the above ſaid <hi>William Caſwel;</hi> the ſaid <hi>Thomas Hull</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken in the ſtreet, by virtue of the aforeſaid Warrant, and carried before <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> who in a fury demanded, how he durſt arreſt his Souldiers? and would not take baile, but ſent him to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and one with him, who only came along with his Friend, the ſaid <hi>Thomas Hull,</hi> and deſired to baile him: Where they both lay about ten or twelve dayes before they could be bail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and were held bound from Seſſions to Seſſions, for a long time after, before they could be diſcharged; So little was the Kings <hi>Proclamation</hi> regarded by <hi>John Robinſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> on the 20th. of <hi>October,</hi> 1661. there came a parcel of the aforeſaid rude Souldiers to the Meeting at <hi>Brick-Lane,</hi> and took away one that was then Preaching: Some there deſired them to ſhew their Warrant for their ſo doing; one Lieutennant <hi>Wilton</hi> ſhewed his Commiſſion as he was an Officer, which being read, he ſaid, that was ſufficient; one anſwering, ſaid, that was not ſufficient, he ought to have a particular Warrant, with the name of the Perſon ſeized, expreſſed in it; and under the Hand and Seal of ſome one Juſtice or more; one Enſigne <hi>Spike,</hi> anſwered, If that were not ſufficient, it was ſufficient Sir <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171597:4"/>he called him, bad them by word of mouth do what they did; to which was anſwered, That a verbal Order from him or any other Juſtice elſe, was not according to Law in ſuch a Caſe; neither did the Law intitle them to be Executioners of it; but if they had a Warrant, as they had none, it ought to be directed to ſome Peace-Officer, and not to them: yet notwithſtanding they carried him away to the Tower, before <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> who ſent him to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> pretending and inſerting great matters in his <hi>Mittimus;</hi> where he lay thirty Weeks without any thing laid to his Charge, and then they releaſed him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> on the third day of <hi>November</hi> 1661. they came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in the like manner to the aforeſaid place, in as rude a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as before, and with as little a ſhew or face of Law, they ſeized him that was preaching (as one was at that time) and when they had taken him down, they took away three more, two of which were ſitting at the Table, whom they carried before <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> who committed them all to <hi>New-Priſon,</hi> inſerting in their <hi>Mittimus,</hi> things of an high nature; as their ſpeaking of treaſonable Words, and the like, who, when ſome queſtioned the Legallity of their ſeizure, he, <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> replyed, with ſome Indignation, <hi>That he ſent them to do what they did;</hi> as if his Verbal Command were ſufficient to juſtifie their illegal Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. And at Seſſions following, there was one of them removed in time of Seſſions, only by <hi>John Robinſons</hi> Warrant from <hi>New-Priſon</hi> to <hi>New-gate;</hi> in order as he ſaid to his Tryal, which he could never attain to have, nor any thing laid to his charge, though he often called for it in the face of the Court; but had no notice taken of him, nor never returned in the Callender; yet was he kept in <hi>Newgate</hi> twelve weeks unjuſtly; till he was fetched out by a Perſon in authority. He ſuffered in all near 18 Weeks Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment; and the reſt of his Fellows ſuffered 28 Weeks Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, and then were releaſed, nothing being laid to their Charge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> the 25 of <hi>May,</hi> 1662. at a Meeting in <hi>Shacksbies-Walk,</hi> near <hi>Wapping Wall,</hi> where ſome People were peaceably met, there came Souldiers in a hoſtile manner with Swords and Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, pulling and halling ſome of them, and the Man that was Preaching they pulled violently down from the place where he ſtood, though it was his own hired Houſe; and ſuch was their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171597:5"/>rage notwithſtanding he was their Priſoner, becauſe he continued ſpeaking, they cryed ſhoot him, before he had any Tryal or was found worthy or not worthy of Death; and ſuch was their vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, that a Child belonging unto the Family, about a Year and a quarter old, was ſo affrighted and awakened out of its ſleep, as it lay in the Cradle, with which fright it fell ſick and never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered its ſickneſs, but died three dayes after; and whether they were the Cauſe of its Death or no, is left to the Lord to determine at the laſt day. They carried two of the ſaid Meeting before <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> who committed them to <hi>Newgate,</hi> were they ſtill remain, nothing being laid to their Charge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> On the ſame 25th. day of <hi>May,</hi> the Souldiers came to <hi>Beech-Lane,</hi> to a Meeting there, with their Swords drawn, pulling and halling of them violently, and two of them they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the morning to <hi>Newgate,</hi> where they were kept, and never had before any Magiſtrate to be heard, nor accuſed by any till the Quarter-Seſſions, which was a Month or five Weeks af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> On the firſt day of <hi>June,</hi> 1662. they came to the aforeſaid <hi>Beech-Lane,</hi> with their Swords drawn as before, the <hi>Enſigne</hi> came in with his Sword drawn, holding of it over the head of him that was Preaching, pulling them violently down the Stairs, carrying them to <hi>Pauls</hi> Yard, and from thence to <hi>Richard Brown,</hi> who committed them to <hi>Newgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> On the ſame firſt day of <hi>June,</hi> 1662. the Souldiers came to <hi>Brick Lane</hi> aforeſaid, in like violent manner, with Swords and Muskets, and forced him that was ſpeaking, down, with great outrage, and carried ten of the men before <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his wonted manner committed them to <hi>New-Priſon;</hi> this was in the Morning, and in the Afternoon they came again with far greater violence, broke the Pulpit all to pieces, they left not a whole piece of Wood, and carried eight more to the Tower before <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> who committed them to <hi>New-Priſon</hi> alſo: But not to omit an Act worthy the obſerving, <hi>John Robinſon</hi> as he came (near night) by the Watch-houſe at <hi>Brick-Lane</hi> End, where the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Souldiers were keeping Guard, they told him what they had done, how they had broken the Pulpit: He <hi>(John Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binſon)</hi> anſwered, It was well done; and gave the Souldiers a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171597:5"/>piece of Gold as a Reward for their good Service.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> On the eighth of <hi>June,</hi> 1662. the Souldiers came again to <hi>Brick-Lane,</hi> Exerciſing their wonted Violence and Tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous behaviour; they carried away ſeven men before <hi>John Robin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> who committed them to <hi>New-Priſon,</hi> where they yet remain. On the ſame eighth day of <hi>June,</hi> the Souldiers came to the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Beech-Lane,</hi> manifeſting their fury and rage; they took away onely him that was Preaching, and carryed him before <hi>Richard Brown;</hi> when the man was before him, amongſt the reſt of his learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed diſcourſe, he told him, he ſhould teach him a new Trade (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as we ſuppoſe, that he would ſend him to <hi>Bridewel</hi>) and have the skin from his Back: He committed him to <hi>Newgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly,</hi> On the fifteenth of <hi>June,</hi> 1662. the Souldiers came again to <hi>Brick-Lane,</hi> in ſuch manner as they were wont, they took ſix men and carried them to <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> who committed them to <hi>Newgate.</hi> And on the ſame day they came to the Meeting at <hi>Beech-Lane,</hi> and violently ſet upon them with drawn Swords, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of them out of their Meeting place with great rage; The place they ſtood to Preach in, they brake it down with ſuch fury, that they broke their Muskets: They ſtruck ſeveral perſons to their detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in point of health. After which, they took two men more, carried them to <hi>Pauls</hi> Yard, and from thence to <hi>Newgate,</hi> where they were kept while Seſſions, not being at all committed or had before any Magiſtrate, and at Seſſions returned to <hi>Newgate,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing being laid to their Charge; where they ſtill remain.</p>
            <p>On the ſame fifteenth of <hi>June,</hi> 1662. the Souldiers came with great fury and rage, with their Swords drawn, to the Meeting at <hi>Petty-France,</hi> where they very inhumanely wounded a Boy almoſt to death; it was doubtful whether he would recover it: They took away him that Preached, and carried him to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and never had him before any Magiſtrate, where he remained till Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and from thence was returned to <hi>Newgate</hi> again, where he yet remains.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tenthly,</hi> On the 29th. of <hi>June,</hi> Souldiers came to <hi>Petty-France,</hi> full of Rage and Violence, with their Swords drawn; they wounded ſome, and ſtruck others, broke down the Gallery, and made much Spoile: This was in the Morning. In the Afternoon the Souldiers came to <hi>Baick-Lane</hi> practiſing their wonted Cruelty, by pulling, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alling, and beating them, and took ſeveral, had them before
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171597:6"/>
               <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> who committed them to <hi>New-Priſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eleventhly,</hi> On the 6th. of the Month called <hi>July,</hi> the Souldiers came like Beaſts of prey to <hi>Brick-Lane,</hi> where they ſhut the Door and kept in all that were there, and with great violence they brake the Forms before their faces, they left not one Form whole, taking the Leggs and hurling them againſt the Glaſs Windows, pulling and halling many, not regarding Sex, Childhood, nor Old Age; they took ſix men, had them before <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> who committed them to <hi>New-Bridewell:</hi> In the morning following, they were by the Keepers of <hi>Bridewell</hi> called to beat Hemp, which they refuſing to do, were put into <hi>New-Priſon</hi> to the reſt of their fellow Sufferers, where they ſtill are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Twelfthly,</hi> On the 27th. of the ſame Month, the Souldiers came to <hi>Brick-Lane</hi> aforeſaid, with a multitude of rude people, as Butch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers out of <hi>White-Chappel,</hi> Bailiffs-followers, Boys, and ſuch like unruly and debauched fellows, with a Conſtable, like themſelves who (as we heard) told <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> That he could not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them, nor break the Meeting at <hi>Brick-Lane. John Robinſon</hi> anſwered (as was ſaid) <hi>That then he ſhould let in the multitude up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and let them tear their Clothes from their backs;</hi> or Words to that purpoſe; which may very well be judged to be true, for the aboveſaid ungodly wretches, Souldiers, and Conſtables, after they had beat, pulled and halled them, in a very inhumane manner, themſelves ſet the great gates wide open; The Conſtable, named <hi>Bartlet,</hi> a Cook, and <hi>Brown</hi> the Marſhal, a wicked lewd fellow calling the rude multitude in, marched down before them, ſaying to them, <hi>Do your Work boyes,</hi> which they did, for they beat the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Maids, broke the Forms, the Glaſs Windows, &amp; the Door making ſuch ſpoil and havock as was ſeldom heard of; ſparing none no not Women big with Child; This <hi>Brown</hi> the Marſhal being asked, Why he beat the Women? he ſaid, <hi>Who ſaw me? who will ſwear it?</hi> And with thoſe words fell more violently upon the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſome whereof were with Child, ſtriking of them with his fiſts ſuch blows that made them reel. Again a Maid had her Bible ſnatched away, ſhe labouring to get it again, was ſtruck over the Eye, that it was black a long time after. Then the Souldiers too ſix men and a Woman, and carried them to <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> who notwithſtanding committed them all to <hi>New-Priſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many other Cruel and inhumane actions, they have committed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171597:6"/>at other times, and in other places, which is hear omitted, which no doubt but the Lord hath taken notice of; and will one day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence it upon the heads of them that were the Actors in it: Now that theſe things are contrary to Law, I think that we need not ſpend Time and waſt Paper to prove the Law alowing no ſuch Violence, but on the contrary, forbids and puniſheth it; but we are content to wait until the Lord ſhall ariſe to plead our Cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirteenthly,</hi> On the third day of the Month called <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1662. when the Priſoners in <hi>Newgate,</hi> called <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> were in their Chamber ſeeking the Lord, and ſpeaking to one another, that they might, as their Duty is, <hi>provoke one another to Love and good Works,</hi> Heb. 10. about four of the Clock in the afternoon, the Thieves, as <hi>Houſe-Breakers, Pick-Pockets, Highway-Men,</hi> came with violence into our Room, one took up a Bible from the Table and threw it down to the ground, asking, what we did there? ſtruck one in the Face with his Fiſt, and he with the reſt fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, drew their Knifes, and indeavoured to Stab ſome of us; but the Lord was pleaſed to deliver us from their Cruelty, for we took courage to defend our ſelves, and eſcaped their Bloody hands; and on the ſame day, the like Violence, as we were informed, was offered to thoſe Brethren in the <hi>White-Lyon, Southwark,</hi> by the Fellons there; and on the firſt of <hi>June,</hi> ſo called, 62. which was upon the firſt day of the Week, after we were brought to Priſon, ſome of the Keepers did come up to us, and charge us that we ſhould not Pray, nor Preach, for if we did, they had order to put us into the Hole, and that they muſt do it: And though that was not executed, yet the Fellons did come violently upon us no our Room, and did beat ſome of us, and threaten us all, ſaying, they would now order us well enough, for they had Commiſſion ſo to do.</p>
            <p>Will not the Stones in the ſtreet cry out (if we ſhould hold our peace) againſt theſe Wicked, Filthy, and Ungodly Proceedings of theſe Wicked men? and is it not the more to be lamented, that ſuch things ſhould be practiſed in a Nation, who profeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be Chriſtians, and the only true Church ſeparated from <hi>Rome?</hi> and yet they follow <hi>Romes</hi> ſteps in Perſecuting the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and all them of different Perſwaſions from them, and that they do in ſuch a way and manner by Violence, Cruelty, Spoile,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171597:7"/>and Blood ſhed, that <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf can hardly exceed them; and the very Heathen would be aſhamed of them, their own Laws they make no Rule, they ſpare not to violate them, though they cry up Obedience to the King, and call ſuch <hi>Rebels</hi> as dare not violate their Conſciences by obeying the King to diſobey God, and Jeſus Chriſt, King of Kings, and of Nations, the only Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver; yet they themſelves regard not the Kings Commands, they put in Execution their own Wills, no man (in Power) controul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, as if every Wicked man, and prophane Blaſphemous Perſon, were left to do in Perſecuting of the Godly, whatſoever ſeemeth good in his own eyes; and as though there were no King in <hi>England;</hi> as if the Lord's People were appointed to be mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and ſlaughtred by them, their Houſes rifled, and yet theſe ſay they are Chriſtians; their Miniſters tell them ſo, and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them in their wicked Wayes, their filthy prophane and lewd doings, and tell them that others be <hi>Hereticks, Schiſmaticks, Sepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, Phanaticks,</hi> and what not? and ſo ſet on the Wicked like a company of greedy Dogs upon harmleſs Sheep, who run upon them with open Mouth, as if they would devour all at once, and make a full end quickly.</p>
            <p>Oh horrible! can theſe men be the Miniſters of Chriſt? and ſuch the Members of Chriſt, that uſe ſuch violence to their Neighbours that the Law of God nor of Nations will not in the leaſt juſtifie them in, is it not <hi>a certain token of Perdition to them?</hi> Phil. 1.28. may they not in their Actions read themſelves Sons of Perdition, the hated of God? <hi>For the Lord tryeth the Righteous, but the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and him that loveth Violence his Soul hateth,</hi> Pſal 11.5. and yet they ſay, they are the true Church, their Miniſters ſay ſo, and therefore all muſt be conformable to them and their wayes, or elſe Perſecute them, Baniſh them, Hang them, they are not worthy to live, they cannot uſe them bad enough. But if there were but one <hi>Gamaliel</hi> amongſt them, he would ſay, <hi>Refrain from theſe men, and let them alone; for if this Counſel, or this Work be of men, it will come to nought, but if it be of God, you cannot overthrow it, leaſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ye be found even to fight againſt God,</hi> Acts 5.38, 39. or were there any as rational as the Heathen, they would not violate their own Lawes, for they mightily ſtood upon it, and were very exact and careful to maintain them, and all thoſe Priviledges that did acrew to any by them; for when they bound <hi>Paul,</hi> and would
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171597:7"/>have ſcourged him, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Is it lawful for you to ſcourge a</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>and uncondemned?</hi> When the <hi>Centurion</hi> heard that, he went and told the chief Captain, ſaying, <hi>Take heed what thou doſt, for this man is a</hi> Roman, &amp;c. <hi>then ſtraight-way they departed from him that ſhould have examined him</hi> (or as the Margent reads it, tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him) <hi>and the chief Captain was afraid after he knew that he was a</hi> Roman, <hi>and becauſe he had bound him,</hi> Acts 22.25, 26, &amp; 27, verſ. They were ſo juſt in their Proceedings, though Heathens, that they would puniſh Injuſtice in any, therefore the chief Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain was afraid, knowing what was done to <hi>Paul,</hi> was done con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Law; but here in a Chriſtian Nation, as they ſay they are, we are beaten, wounded, pulled and halled, our Goods ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and broken, and we free-born <hi>Engliſh</hi> men and uncondemned, and no notice taken of it; the chief Captains, <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> and <hi>Richard Brown</hi> are not afraid, but rather countenance than reprove the Violence that is offered at this day; and is it not much to be lamented, that ſuch wicked and ungodly Aſſemblies, as <hi>Stage-Plaies, Popit-Plaies, Bear-Baitings, Prizes,</hi> going about the ſtreets with Drums, their Swords drawn, drawing many lewd Perſons after them to their ungodly Sports and prophane Paſtimes, <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdancing,</hi> ſetting up <hi>May-Poles,</hi> and meeting to <hi>Dance</hi> about them, <hi>dancing</hi> for <hi>Garlands</hi> in many Streets, <hi>Revellings, Whitſon-Ales,</hi> and the like, by which Youth is nouriſhed and hardened in Vice and Vanity, many times to the utter ruin both of Body and Soul; by the means of which wicked prophane Meetings, and Aſſemblings, <hi>Blaſphemy, Swearing, Curſing, Quarrelling, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Adultery, Contempt of God,</hi> his <hi>Word</hi> and true <hi>Worſhip,</hi> is uſhered in; many Families impoviſhered, and Wifes and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſit at home with hungry Bellies; and that which may not be forgotten, the Curſes and Judgements of God hangs over this poor Nation, and are threatned againſt it for theſe their ungodly deeds, and all this is ſuffered, none making any attempt to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs them; but in ſuch Meetings appointed for the Service and Worſhip of God, where his Word is purely taught, his Ordinances adminiſtred rightly according to the Primitive Inſtitution, and his People in the name and fear of Chriſt aſſembled, whom they can charge with nothing but in the matters of God, they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continently taken and abuſed, thrown into Priſon, there kept amongſt common Fellons, who are deſperately bent to harm them,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171597:8"/>did not the Lord protect and keep his poor People, as though God were like unto them, to delight more in <hi>Maygames</hi> and <hi>Stage-Playes,</hi> &amp;c. than in the ſolemn Aſſemblies of his People: Oh! <hi>England, England,</hi> What wilt thou do when the Lord enters into a controverſie with thee, thou City of <hi>London,</hi> to whom God hath ſhewed ſo many Mercies, to whom God hath given ſuch Means, and ſuch plenty of the Means of Grace; what Nation hath had ſuch Means as <hi>England?</hi> And what City hath God ſhowered down ſuch Flouds of Mercy and Grace upon, as he hath upon <hi>London,</hi> and yet how hath <hi>England</hi> and <hi>London</hi> required the Lord? what have been the fruit of that rich mercy of the Goſpel, that thou haſt had? will God accept of <hi>Violence, Tumults, Blood-ſhed, Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Curſing,</hi> as <hi>Dam'um, Sink'um,</hi> and many ſuch Execrations, fearful belching forth of <hi>Blaſphemies,</hi> provoking him to his very face, by daring him to deſtroy them, and confound them; thinkeſt thou oh <hi>England,</hi> that God accepts of <hi>Bear-baitings, Tavern-hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, drinking Healths,</hi> while they wallow in the filth and mire of their uncleanneſs; no no, theſe things are an abomination to the pure and holy God, and theſe things will haſten his Wrath, and bring down his Fury upon thee, if thou repent not, and break off theſe crying Sins by Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>But to return, what ſhall we ſay, can this be a Chriſtian Nation? can any man that hath his eyes in his head, ſee any Chriſtianity, or any likeneſs of Chriſt amongſt them? did he ever give them any ſuch example, as to perſecute any for Conſcience? hath not he left this charge with his Miniſters, by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The Servant of God muſt not ſtrive, but be gentle to all men, apt to teach, Patient, in Meekneſs inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, if God peradventure will give them Repentance, to the acknowledgement of the Truth,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.24, 25. <hi>and again he muſt be one that holds faſt the faithful Word, as he hath been taught, that he may be able by ſound Doctrine, both to exhort and convince the Gain-Sayers, Titus</hi> 1.9. <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> to whom this Word was writ, were <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and we have ſome men that ſay they are <hi>Biſhops</hi> now, but were they ſuch as Chriſt would own to be ſuch, then would they be gentle, and not ſtrive, yea they would be gentle to all men, although they were <hi>Hereticks,</hi> (as they ſay we are) and though it ſhould be granted, we <hi>oppoſe our ſelves</hi> againſt the truth, yet is it their duty in meekneſs to <hi>inſtruct us,</hi> and not to ruinate us; and if they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171597:8"/>ſay we are <hi>Gain-ſayers,</hi> then ought they by ſound Doctrine to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us,</hi> and not by ſuch inhumane and violent dealings think to <hi>Proſelyte us,</hi> for that is not the Way of God but of the Devil, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. and therefore had they the Truth as they have not, they would be willing to take the courſe the Apoſtle directs to.</p>
            <p>Were they Biſhops as they ſay they are, but are not, they would be willing to come forth by ſound Doctrine, and Scripture-authority, to convince us that they are Biſhops, and that Chriſt the Head of the Church, hath called, choſen, and appointed them to be Lord-Biſhops, Archbiſhops, or Biſhops, and that their wayes of Worſhip are agreeable to the mind of Chriſt contained in the Scriptures: Their ſprinkling Babes, their Common-prayer, their Holy Garments (as they ſay they are) as Lawn-ſleeves, Tippets, Caps, Surplices, with many more Veſtments; Their Organs, and other Wind-Muſick which they uſe, with Singing-Men and Boyes, and many more ſuch like things; then ſhall we ſubmit to it, and acknowledge we have been miſtaken and miſſed: But if they will uſe no other Arguments than ſuch down right Blowes as we now have, they will never convince us that they are the Miniſters of Chriſt, or their wayes the good Old Way we ſhould walk in: For was it ever known that <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> Cudgeled people into the way of the Goſpel? Can it be imagined that they Convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and Converted any by impriſoning them, or any ſuch like way? Nay on the contrary, they themſelves were Perſecuted, Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Scourged, and commanded not to Preach any more in the name of Jeſus; Yet would they not forbear, becauſe it was better to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey God rather than man. And truly though it may not be univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally true, that every one that is perſecuted is therefore a good Chriſtian, yet this is moſt certain and univerſally true, that they that do perſecute any for Conſcience or Religion, are at the beſt but bad Chriſtians; for thoſe that are in the true Faith and Fear of the moſt High, that worſhip the Lord in Spirit and in Truth, are by Jeſus Chriſt ſaid to be his ſheep; now we know that ſheep are of ſuch a nature that they will not deſtroy, no nor harm others, but are as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>ſent forth amongſt Wolves,</hi> which are of a quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary nature, Beaſts of prey, and very ravenous: Such differences there are between the Perſecuted, and the Perſecutors, the true Church and the falſe: For the people of the Lord were grievouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſecuted in moſt Ages, it was given to them to ſuffer for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171597:9"/>Chriſts ſake: And <hi>they that would live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, ſuffered Perſecution,</hi> as ſaith the Scriptures. But we never heard of any of them, to wit the true Churches of Chriſt, or his true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſters, that did ever Perſecute any for Conſcience, or took that courſe to convince Gain-ſayers; but they laboured night and day in the Word, approving themſelves by ſound Doctrine to every man's Conſcience, that ſo they might be profitable to the Souls of Men, and finiſh the Miniſtry that they had received of the Lord; they counted not their Lives dear unto them, but expoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Hunger, Nakedneſs, and to an innumerable company of Sufferings, and never were Lords and Rulers of Nations, neither were they called of men <hi>Rabby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, except our Conſciences be Convinced by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and ſound Reaſon, that we are in the Wrong, and the Biſhops, ſo called, in the Right, it is not beating and halling of us to Priſon, and ſpoiling of our Goods, nor greater matters than all that will do it: For though it may be thought by ſome rebellion, and by ſome others imprudence to keep up our Meetings when we are forbid, yet ſuch is our reſpect to the Law of God, and Chriſt our Lord who died for us, that we cannot but obey him rather then men: and indeed do eſteem our Meetings, and the Ordinances of God more dear to us, than our Eſtates, Relations, nay than our very Lives, what ever may be thought of us, or how ever we may be preſented by any; Neither do we doubt but that the Lord who is our Light and Salvation, and the ſtrength of our Life, will enable us to endure the Croſs, and diſpiſe the Shame, what ever it be that may he inflicted on us; for this we know, that the Captain of our Salvation, Jeſus, to whom we look, went before us in ſuffering, and if they perſecuted the green tree, much more will they perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the dry, and if they called the Maſter of the houſe <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> how much more ſhall they call them of his houſhold, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.25. And if they ſaid of him, [Chriſt] <hi>He hath a Devil, and is mad, why hear ye him?</hi> much more will they ſay of his followers, they are <hi>Phanaticks.</hi> What our Lord went before us in, he in his rich and free Love hath made us willing for to follow after, and doubt not but he will give us more ſtrength, and make us yet more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſuffer for his ſake, what Tribulations ſoever we may meet with, having a good Conſcience, (and that is to us a continual feaſt) void of offences towards God and towards them: knowing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171597:9"/>they cannot juſtly accuſe us of any thing that we have done, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it be that we are faithful and conſtant to what we know of Chriſt, and will not ſubmit to any thing that is of humane Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and contrary to the Light of our Conſciences; and in this we can rejoyce, and be exceeding glad, <hi>becauſe great is our reward in Heaven,</hi> it being a choice favour from the Lord, who accounteth us worthy to ſuffer ſhame for his Name; and though we may ſuffer more than yet we have done, yet this we know, that God will at length ariſe and plead our Cauſe, and judge between Us and our Perſecutors. Then let ſuch take heed, the Lord will one day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge his Elect, that cry day and night unto him, though he bear long with them; I tell you, ſaith Chriſt, he will avenge them ſpeedily, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.7, 8. <hi>For the day of vengeance is in his heart, and the Year of his Redeemed will come, and though there be none to help, nor none to uphold, yet his own Arm ſhall bring Salvation,</hi> Iſa. 53.4, 5. Let the Lords people therefore Labour to be found in a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient waiting for the coming of Chriſt, <hi>He that ſhall come will come and will not tarry;</hi> and then he will give a reward to every one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their works, with whom there is no reſpect of Perſons in judgement; whoſe is the Kingdom, the Power, and the Glory, now and for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>VVE would not be underſtood by any, that we ſend out this</hi> Cry <hi>becauſe we are wearied with what we have ſuffered, or afraid of what we may further ſuffer; but that we might ſhew to the World that our Sufferings are altogether contrary to Law and Humanity it ſelf: For did they no more than were Law, we ſhould be ſilent, and willing with much rejoycing to endure and ſuffer it in that bleſſed Cauſe of the Goſpel, which we are not aſhamed of, nor of the Teſtimony of the Lord Jeſus, for whom we are willing to ſuffer the loſs of all things, eſteeming it a very choice Mercy that the Lord ſhould accept of ſuch poor nothing and unworthy Creatures as we are, to bear a teſtimony for him, againſt Idolatry and Prophaneneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
